this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software support for SC radio comes from
the O'Reilly velocity conference join
over 2000 developers and engineers in
San Jose from June 19th through the 22nd
to learn how resilience engineering can
make your systems more scalable reliable
and efficient get the latest on
containers micro services infrastructure
cloud devops systems engineering
security and more while you meet experts
and network with peers use discount code
se 22 save 20% on your gold silver or
bronze pass
that's se 2-0 get all the details at
velocity conf comm / CA for software
engineering radio this is Robert bloomin
today I have with me James
Turnbull James is the CTO and padico
prior to that he was CTO a Kickstarter
and has been in leadership roles at
docker venmo and puppet labs James is
the author of 10 books about open source
software including the art of monitoring
the log stash book the docker book the
terraform book and multiple books about
puppet James welcome back to software
engineering radio reason I say welcome
back is you are on an earlier show about
docker will link to that in the show
notes today we'll be talking mostly
about terraform maybe some puppet and
use that as a way to explore the area of
declarative programming before we start
would you like to add anything about
yourself that I didn't cover no I do
have a funny accent for those people
about to listen so it's a who were just
gonna start yeah so anyone who's a
puzzled about what I'm saying just slow
it down and I you should go get ready
we have listeners all over the world
it's about 40% in the u.s. so I'm sure
people are used to dealing with all
kinds of English accents but thanks for
the clarification I'm gonna start out
with Tara form what is Tara form and
what problem does it solve Tara forms an
open-source tool by looking at a hash
akak who are you may be familiar with to
have a number of open source projects
including console which is a service
discovery tool and probably most
narrative developers vagrant which is a
local virtual machine environment that's
a lot of developers used to set up local
testing and local development
environments terraform itself is an
infrastructure management tool
so essentially inside the sort of
infrastructure management well there's a
concept calling the structure of code
which is essentially a way of saying you
want to cool things like servers and
services and you can codify those you
know in some format puppet does a
similar thing and terraform consumes
that code connects to a bunch of
infrastructure services and
infrastructure tools and spits out
configured services example common
commonly used in the AWS Amazon world
where you can say I'd like to have an
ec2 instance and it needs to be
configured this way and have this
particular set of attributes and so I
created a terraform configuration that
configures it and I launched that
configuration and terraform goes off to
Amazon and creates me the required
instruction I wanted to mention to our
listeners we have done shows on console
vagrant docker and infrastructure as
code a link to all those in the show
notes now back to our discussion I have
worked at jobs where when we wanted
infrastructure on Amazon we would go
onto their console press some buttons or
run a script that hits their API why is
a terraform approach possibly better
than those other approaches to creating
infrastructure there's a couple of
reasons
the first one is that
when you go into the console and press
all those buttons and create the
infrastructure let's say you
accidentally delete some of that
infrastructure and one of your
colleagues has to go back and recreate
all he has to basically reach shapes or
she has to be truly trace your steps
through the console and click all the
right buttons and make all the right
configuration changes and if you haven't
used the Amazon console it's up the only
complex set of applications and services
for example I think the ec2 tab inside
the AWS console probably has 40
configuration items like each driving
driving down the submenus
so what terraform does is allows you to
say instead of you going to the console
you can actually declaratively describe
describe the state of your instructor's
you wanted like an ec2 instance I would
like an RDS instance for my database I
would like some an elastic load balancer
as my load balancer and I would like to
be configured in this particular way
with these ports open and and these this
particular specific configuration of
memory and disk and so on and then I can
create it and the next type of person
that comes along couldn't replicate that
configuration or technically because
essentially it's like a manifest or the
source code and that's always the second
reason which is that it becomes
something you can actually make part of
your source code so instead of to keep
out like your source code is purely the
code that drives your application you
start thinking of source code as the
things that builds your infrastructure
upon which you are going to install your
application and upon which you get a
sort of deploy and that opens up a whole
variation in world around the concept of
infrastructure testing infrastructure
continuous delivery continuous pipelines
for disruption I understand from your
description that terraform
consumes source code the developers
create podcast is not a great medium for
discussing source code but could you
give a little bit of a feeling of what
kind of source code terraform takes as
input sure so terraform is two inputs
one is called HDL which is a it is a a
hash equal produced configuration
language so it's effectively a she
called DSL
it's very close to think about it it
looks like probably the closest
equivalent is JSON which is the other
language that terraform or consumers you
can write your configuration your
infrastructure sauce in JSON or in this
HCl language which is kind of like a
more human readable form of JSON I think
everyone's familiar with dropping a
comma here and there in JSON and JSON
linking is a non-trivial problem HCl is
a way of presenting a more human
readable version of JSON use a term DSL
that would be domain-specific language I
apologize that's okay it's kind of my
job to to make sure the terms get
defined I wouldn't mention that because
we've had some shows on that as well so
I'm gonna link to those now suppose that
I want to build three different database
clusters in my environment and they're
kind of similar but they differ in some
minor ways to terraform off or anything
like a function call or module where I
can run the same code more than once
not exactly the same way each time it
certainly does so one of the really
attractive things about terraform is
that it is a modular environment so I
can for example create a default RDS of
database in the case of a diverse or
database module that configures the
standard things I care about in my
database the basic configuration I can
then for amortize some items in that
configuration for example I could say
other data the size of the database for
example I could say that I would like to
run it on this particular size in test
this particular size in staging and then
a much larger box for production when I
do my terraform configuration I can
include the database module and I can
parameterize it based on where I am so
for example I say I'm running in the
development environment and that may be
you know set up with a environment
variable or maybe a bit of something a
very real passing into the your
configuration somewhere or query from a
data store of some kind by passing that
variable saying this is the production
environment and based on that variable
terraform makes a number of decisions
about how it's going to configure that
database you could have three
environment
like many shops QA staging and
production but you don't need to have
three really similar almost identical
sets of terraform files in order to
build out those three environments then
that's okay you mentioned three very
interesting applications for this one
was infrastructure testing talk about
that so I think one of the really neat
things about sort of changing the way
we've deployed in the structure of the
years is that it's a cat become closer
to the sort of software development
world rather than sort of previous in
the past mr. Merseyside means and
operations people really didn't have a
lot of software development practices
and the way they look infrastructure and
the way they manage their infrastructure
and one of the things that we picked up
from the software world community for
example is version of trial so very
rarely do you find environments these
days where cease admins are not putting
configuration into version control one
of these new things that came out of
that and the concept of the
infrastructure is code is that we
thought okay there are some other good
software developer actors that it may be
weekend adult so one of the first ones
that sort of looked at was testing and
it was to say that okay if I can write
unit tests for my applications or source
code you know for example something that
determines that you know input and input
goes into this method and the app word
should be this thing you know I could
write a unit test for that maybe I can
do the same thing for infrastructure so
I know that when infrastructure needs to
be a MySQL database open on port 3306
and it needs to have a user called
production that when I connect to it
responds and validates my connection
needs to have three databases president
maybe QA stage in the production so how
about I run a unit test for that for
each of those and essentially what what
um infrastructures code allows you doing
application like to Oracle is that I can
locally in my environment I can run my
terraform configuration I can create my
my school database and then I can use a
variety of testing tools and there are a
few of them test kitchens is a pretty
common one and basically what it does is
it says this infrastructure should
respond to the thing they should have a
test that says this infrastructure
should answer on port 3306 it should
have a user call for action
and it should have three databases if it
doesn't spit out an error and what I can
do is I can wrap my infrastructure build
in the same process that I would use my
continuous deployment or continuous
delivery or even just my test cycle for
my application so when I do my
deployment for example I go from the
staging environment to production
environment or the QA environment to
staging and what I can do is that I can
say my instructor changes and my
application changes are all in source
code my test my test process is that see
my Jenkins server or my circle or
whatever happened testing tool I use
execute Smike my instructor tests which
builds all of the required
infrastructure the databases of my
balances and and servers it runs a bunch
of tests to make sure they configured
correctly then it may run all of my
infrastructure tests and create my
required artifacts like a jar file or a
war file and then deploy that to my
freshly build infrastructure and then
run all of my integration or acceptance
tests and the end of it I know that
everything in my environment from the
bottom piece of infrastructure right up
to the application source code is green
all the way and I can say okay that's a
valid build and deploy rather to have
things that happen like my application
source code of the components in piles
fine or my tests pass
I create my artifacts and I deployed in
production turns out you know someone in
the staging environment decided to
change the name of the database but I
didn't know because someone manually
changed the stage environment that's not
changing production and mine built my
deploy or my application falls over this
starts to remove the same sort of
problems that gets the design to
identify applications let's go remove
those from infrastructure
I've definitely seen problems due to
people making manual changes in
infrastructure to get a test to work and
then it breaks when you move it to
another environment this would imply
that when you adopt terraform and you
check your terraform files in to get you
run them through this pipeline that no
one is allowed to make manual changes on
the infrastructure that terraform built
is is that a valid conclusion yeah one
of the classic problems
structure world and for us that means is
that entropy happens like you know I
identify a problem with through the
morning with video infrastructure I make
a configuration change to it I go back
to sleep
the next team the team wakes up in the
morning and don't realize that I've made
that change you know and it doesn't
enter a recorded history or it doesn't
there's no version control so over time
a number of these changes accumulate and
when I go to actually sort of deploy my
code again or rebuild that environment
like there's no record of those manual
changes so all of a sudden my running
environment has deviated dramatically
from my what I think the world looks
like and you know obviously I don't have
to either replicate all of those changes
or against roll forward until I have an
environment that works you know that the
advantage of the sort of immutable model
is that is that I can say don't change
anything in production what in fact what
I want to do is I want to change things
in my source code and then redeploy okay
so infrastructure is immutable but it
needs to change over time for many
reasons how do you manage those changes
to ensure that they don't create
instability so the way to manage those
changes they treat them like any sort of
software patch or software update you
maintain them in your source code follow
the same protocol you use to make
application sauce changes so you know
you are you make a change you tested it
works you create a pull requests on the
code abuser emerge the code you deploy
it into testing environments you build
that environment you run your tests and
so on and so forth so you actually treat
it exactly would like a bit of software
source code and then you actually treat
the changes the same way so if it's all
in version control you know I have a
commit which contains my latest
infrastructure build I just pushed that
commit out to my floor would we care for
muscles like that and automatically
rebuilds or changes the environment just
soup I don't know what the change I want
to make obviously it's not possible in
every environment but it's very
attractive for environments like the
attain Erised environments with tools
like docker where the infrastructure and
the data work separately the
infrastructure is effectively stateless
for example like a cost of stateless web
servers or you know our pool of
middleware tools or messaging
infrastructure
I have some experience with another tool
called puppet which is very similar in
spirit to terraform I don't know if
we'll end up talking about that a lot
today but its runs on a single server
and it ensures that all your
configuration files have the correct
value if you go and manually edit a
config file you'll find after the next
puppet run that puppet has replaced it
with whatever it's supposed to be do you
have the same model in terraform where
you tell this is what I want the world
to look like and if the world isn't
exactly like that it will apply some
diffs to the world to make it look like
what was specified yeah a terrible max
there's a lot in common with puppet that
they have a very similar heritage and
Mitchell actually moto who wrote a lot
of was the architect of a lot of the
hash table tools was a very long time
puppet user and very familiar with the
stack
so like puppet terraform is a model
based system so essentially what it does
is it has two modes one's a plan mode
and the other ones that apply mode
pretty much like puppets Noah and apply
modes so what it does is I can make a
change to the infrastructure like I make
maybe I changed the size of a ec2
instance I then run terraform in its
plan mode and a week terraform will
reach out to AWS and say that the
instance is actually this other size on
the new strategy if you apply this
configuration I'm going to change the
size of that instance and then you know
I can determine whether that's a change
I'm comfortable making in which case a
run terraform and it's an apply mode and
I'll update all of my changes but it
allows me to do things like model
changes so I can say if I change this
this or this I run terraform that's plan
boat and it spits out a list of the
changes that it's going to make if you
like them you say oh I'm okay with that
and then it makes them in the apply mode
right great we've been talking a lot so
far about terraforming infrastructure
the show has a long history of doing
many shows on programming languages I
wanted to approach this topic from a
programming language standpoint
terraform is an example of declarative
and we're gonna talk more in depth about
that let's start with imperative
programming which most people learn
their first programming language will be
an imperative language what is an
imperative programming language well at
the simplest form that occurred a
program they would just something like
like bash shell scripts or Ruby or
Python essentially what it is is when
you whenever you tell the application
that you give it you write down the
steps you're going to take so that an
imperative program is where things like
sample X I like to use this like a proto
program so it people like a checklist so
what you do is you say in order to
achieve that was all I want I need I
need a bunch of steps so step one I
create an object step two I make some
change to the object step three I delete
the object and you know declarative
world I only care about the end state of
the object so instead of writing down
all the steps I tell her I tell the
application I would like an object and
she look like this and then I won't I
let the the program or the application
worry about the details those steps I
don't tell that it needs to create it I
don't tell it going to create need to do
this this and this I just say I want
this object and I assume that under the
covers the application knows what it
needs to do declarative languages are
fairly popular I don't know if people
think of them in this way but could you
give examples that you think people have
already used I think the classic one
that people probably don't realize that
the kind of languages pretty much any
database query language so SQL for
example is a declarative language you're
saying to an SQL statement now I would
like to select all the records that meet
these criteria you don't know what's
going to happen underneath the covers
often to your detriment point when it a
query goes disastrously wrong but since
it what you're saying is I want this
data set from this source with these set
of set of criteria you don't know what
the what the database engine is doing
under the surface to to grab the records
from the right tables and the right
fields and one star tours and stuff all
you're saying is oh what this data set
regular expressions are a similar thing
probably not quite as precise and
analogy but a similar set of constructs
and a lot of functional programming
languages where you're trying to avoid
mutation of some kind or were you
actually saying that you know what my
base function I want to achieve some
some result I don't really care how I
get that result as long as Italy does
this why do you think the declarative
model is a good model for the problem
domain of terraform I think it's because
I know I will give the facetious answer
first which is that all C segments are
inherently lazy people and if I don't
have to remember which part of the ideas
console to go to or which 10 AWS API
endpoints and all of the variables to
pass them in order to create that the
stack of things that I I want then no
III I want like all I have to do is say
I would like an AWS environment that
looks like this and terraform doesn't
proposal creates it for me that saves me
a lot of stuff that I would otherwise
have to puzzle out on my own I rely on
the vendor in this case actually co-op
and the members of the open-source
community - we all know remember the
detail of how that infrastructure works
I don't have to care about it the simple
reason that puppet is very popular
system means is that if you work in a
Linux or UNIX environment you don't have
to remember how a bunch of commands work
or more importantly the differences
between those commands across multiple
systems for example starting and
stopping services on RedHat Ubuntu
Debian and Fedora vary between versions
so I remember like how do I compare
style and stop a service or how do I
manage set that service across three
different distributions across four
different versions like every one of
those commands is subtly different it's
a waste of my time to act remember that
stuff when I can pay a computer or use a
computer to do the same mechanism so
this is just leads because it's a
Productivity goal and I should not
remember that stuff but more importantly
I think it's actually about modeling and
it's about seeing the world as a an
insight that I want to achieve and
converging towards that end state while
that's in the world is a series of steps
which can be very easily you know like
all checklist can be very easily broken
quite inserts and updates and changes I
can reason about a declarative world in
a way that I can't did in a narrative
world because I know what my insides
gonna be and I know what my college
studies and I can measure the difference
do you give an example what are some
ways that you could reason about model
that might be difficult if it was a big
Ruby script so the classic want to think
about is firewall rules is the one I I
think about all time but one of my very
first serious jobs was managing a
large-scale infrastructure including
huge firewalls that means had thousands
of rules in them and a subtle change in
that file warm like a script we wanted
to say change of underwear dresses could
have dramatic implications for more than
one part of the system because I wasn't
able to actually see what else might
change is impacted so let's say let's
say I changed an IP address it turned
out that I thought the IP address was
localized to this one application but it
turns out is using these ten other
applications and by making that change I
break those ten other applications
because I haven't updated the IP address
there you know model-driven in a
declarative world all of my resources
that have some relationship I'll link
them together so that IP address is a
graph based model world like a tool like
puppet provides I can walk that graph
and identify all of the instances all of
the nodes in the graph where that IP
address appears which means if I run
that script and I asked puppet to tell
me what's going to happen if I change
this IP address people walk the graph
find all of the nodes that are affected
and tell me that those are the ten
applications that they're also be
affected and that change will take place
I can't do that with a long script a
batch Oh Ruby script or some like that
because I only know what's happening at
that point in time like ten steps down
the road I have no idea what's gonna
happen whereas if I can expect look at
the model and compare with the state I
mean now at the state I want to achieve
I know that you can have a four attack
and I anticipate so you can think about
States something like sets and you can
say what is the intersection yet between
these two sets or
diff between them that's an exact thing
the Venn diagram said like that there's
a number of metaphors that work really
well for this sort of concept and I
think particularly I think software
developers think about this like this is
a quite unnatural phenomenon to them the
concept of comparing a set with another
set and the overlap between them this is
a fairly basic construct for a lot of
user structure people this was a new
concept when when people first started
talking about infrastructures code and
declaratory things so in many ways it
ignites for a lot of lot of folks in
operations world it getting their heads
around this was a non-trivial problem
was there a culture change that had to
occur for acceptance of this approach
yeah there was and I think you touched
on it earlier when you when you talked
about like making my new changes to
infrastructure you know people had to
sort of say okay hands off I'm actually
gonna let the tool when I make a change
at the tool level you know and then you
know rerun my my process or my my tool
will compare the difference and then
deploy that which is what for the most
case most software developers would
think about it's like there's a there's
a spurious bit of output or the
applications behaving in it you know the
wrong ways is you go back to the source
code you identify the bug you write a
fix
you know you deploying the fix or and
the test or associated test and you
deploy it that that whole methodology of
taking that approach was something that
if it starts of people had to adopt or
had to become accustomed to and it's not
a it's not a it's not a natural thing if
you're a lot of infrastructure people
are very tinkerer II like so the natural
thing is to jump on the box and make the
configuration change to get things up
money again rather than treat it like no
this is a bug you know I should treat
like a boat I should ride a patch I
should have test that patch I should
deploy and I should say that's also the
case why people make things worse by
getting on the box and making that
change because they don't understand the
broader implications of what that looks
like the simple fix
turns out the simple fix actually made
the situation worse
this is an example of the DevOps mindset
bringing the sensibilities processes
from the software development world to
the domain of managing systems very much
sir
I think that the early Patrick Dubois
who is one of the earliest of folks who
joined the phrase DevOps was primarily a
developer by trade and when he started
do have introduced a new infrastructure
I didn't work the reason he came up with
a once was he was like there's a bunch
of process and a bunch of my thinking
about things that are a way that could
sort of advantage or help helping
structure people do things better
obviously there's a collaboration piece
there as well but definitely the sort of
process and tooling constructs or things
he thought would be very attractive in
that intersection work I promise little
while ago I wanted to approach this from
a programming language standpoint delve
more into terraform you'd said early on
that the programmer specifies terraform
in json or a similar format you feed it
in to terraform I am gonna guess there's
something like a compiler in a back-end
could you walk us through what happens
when you say terraform what happens to
create the end State so so I first
affine my telephone calls them resources
so a resource can be something like a HP
PC to instance or a database or a DNS
entry any form of sort of infrastructure
or or configuration that I want to build
so I define that in either in it is a
JSON object or as in this HCl hash table
configuration language it has a title
and the title has made of identifiers it
the type of thing it is so it's a react
buggy AWS ec2 instance I give it a name
it might be my web server and I give it
a set of attributes so I tell it that
it's this issue two instances this big
it has this much memory this much disk
the networkers configured this way maybe
there's a
in there that tells it how to you know
it store some software and they go give
it some security rules like I tell it
like these ports are open and these
ports are closed okay I'm gonna
interrupt your what you just described
you're summarizing what would the input
look like to reticular run of Terra
firme okay great so keep going so from
there terraform has the concept of
providers and providers are essentially
a link to the infrastructure tool you
want to work with so for example is an
AWS provider that connects essentially
is that acts as a a wrapper around the
AWS API okay so it essentially provides
an interface to the AWS API so what I do
is I as part of my configuration I
define that provider as well so i say i
want to use AWS to create this resource
and i'm going to say select AWS region
US east one so let me stop you can hear
now all your examples so far have been
AWS but from what you're saying
terraform does not only have the ability
to create resources in AWS it could
create resources on some other kind of
back-end as long as the provider has the
ability to talk to it programmatically
is that right great so it supports much
as your sports CenturyLink why our cloud
stack teaching lotion Google cloud
Heroku free you name a service it
probably supports it in some way you can
do things like work with my school
databases or work with github
repositories or monitoring and
management tools like you relic
OpenStack servers DNS providers you know
you know that there's pretty much a
provider free so most of the major piece
of infrastructure even stuff like
on-premise things like being with this
year and big clouds irregular and stuff
like that okay to summarize and we've
got the input and you've got a range of
providers that know how to talk to
whatever that service is and tell that
service to create different resources
with and if I've requested a certain
type
of rule in my firewall then your
provider knows how to tell the service
to implement that rule in the firewall
correct so what happens I've got so I've
got that configuration I run like my
traditional model as I would run at
what's called the plan command to a
phone plan essentially what happens
there is that it tells you what it's
going to do it doesn't make any changes
so it's essentially a way to await a
model the change before you actually
make it then if I run if I run that
command then terraforming sucks in my
inputs connects to my provider and says
what's the current state of things and
terraform has a concept of state so it
has a concept of what what's happening
now if this is a brand-new configuration
then the state is zero like it doesn't
have anything new but if you've run this
command before telephone plan before and
you've you know you've sucked in your
inputs there may be some existing
resources and terraformers essentially
applies an identifier to each of those
resources and writes out a sort of a
state file and you can store those state
files in either as a perfect on flat
file or in a database or console is
commonly used for example so it goes out
it checks the current state and says you
know what's what's the world will get
like out there
and then it says ok we've got some some
current state like the status quo got
some new things let's compare and see if
there's any differences and then it
identifies you know essentially a
Prince's essentially like a graph based
model so it tent afire all of the
current state and the new state works
out what resources are linked to one
another for example it knows by
interrogating there a Amazon API into
the provider or the as your API provider
that this instance is linked to this
security route for this firewall or this
instance is linked to this elastic load
balancer so it knows that certain
changes are going to have an impact on
more than one resource so for example if
I delete and instance in as your
instance or or a negative in this
instance then I need to also delete that
from the pool of service on my load
balancer if it works this way
that model identifies all of the
leakages together it then validates that
the changes you want to make actually
feasible like so example you might you
might do something that you can't do
finding that like something that can't
be deleted without like a sequencing
problem he tries to puzzle out those
sequences on its own that sometimes it
gets stuck because it's like this can be
very complex other things if then comes
up with effectively what is a an
execution plan and order of things that
it's going to do things so I know is
that going to delete this file will rule
before I delete this other objects and
then I'm gonna recreate this other
people before I can build this next
thing it then spits out to the users and
output which basically is a plan saying
this is that what the end state would
look like and here's the difference from
the previous day you can save those
plans to importantly the one of the
relations about California so I can
actually you know plan out what's going
to happen I can save that plan and then
I can take it somewhere else and execute
it so that by example is a very good way
if they are true terraform changes very
much like a patch management system so I
can create a local if of the changes I
can bundle those changes up and then
apply them in production just like I
would deploy a change set or a patch set
on my environment so I look at that I
see the output I look at that I decide
that okay it's going to change the three
resources it's going to update these two
resources in the latest one resource and
create some new resources uncomfortable
that's the right decision so then I go
okay I'm gonna run the terraform up high
command it sucks in the same inputs
compares it against the state again and
then actually performs the action so it
actually executed the process this
podcast is supported by Atlantic dotnet
hosting solution provider of healthcare
HIPAA PCI compliance and ad tech if
you're feeling the pain of having
outdated technology call atlanticnet and
get the latest security firewall
intrusion detection backup disaster
recovery and virtualization or if you're
starting a new project or not getting
the results you want from your car
providers atlanticnet can help you
succeed
the fully audited solutions in 23 years
in business they won't let you down
visit atlanticnet to learn more you
talked earlier about the idea of a graph
being an important intermediate step
let's start briefly define what a graph
is and then I'll talk some more about
how this graph figures into the
terraform plan sure what care for music
the backend is effectively dependency
graph from a directed graph so
essentially it represents the
dependencies of objects towards lava so
you can actually derive like that as I
talked about before this sort of works
out the order of things it derives that
order from the relationships or the
dependencies between objects so if the
igniters for example that in as your
land if there's an as your server that
as your server has a bunch of dependent
objects for example a fire will rule or
a network interface it knows that you
can't delete the azure object without
deleting the network interface or the
firewall first for example so it walks
along the graph that says this
dependency needs to happen before this
other than energy graph then it has
nodes and edges in this case the nodes
are resources that you're trying to
create and edges are dependencies
between these resources that would
govern the order that they're created in
or deleted in am I getting that right
yeah so it's a set of vertices connected
by edges or vertices nodes could connect
connected by edges and the edges have
have a relationship a direction and
pendency with them associated with them
so that so that those those nodes you
know can be you know you know what
sequence those nodes have to be touched
in now in in puppet which I'm more
familiar with it has a very similar
model you as a programmer are creating
a lot of these edges yourself where you
say this module I'm in it needs these
other modules to happen first or after I
finished doing this thing in this module
I mean then tell this other module that
I'm done because it needs to know that
I'm done now in terraform do the edges
mostly result from things of programmers
specified or does care form have some
more built-in knowledge of the domain
where it knows ok we need to do all the
firewalls first before we set up the
things that are in this part of the
network yeah so that's probably the
primary I mean otherwise I would say the
term form of Papantoniou identical in
the implementation approaches the
primary differences as you said in
puppet it's very common to have to
actually declare relationships in
objects and I think the primary reason
for that is that most of the objects
that you're managing in puppet do not
have a defined API so you often if you
look at a puppet resource and drill down
into the source code also what they are
shelling out to a UNIX command or you're
performing some action where you know
that it's hard to reason about what
might happen as a result of that like
lots of different you could get lots of
different responses from executing a
user add command or a service start or
stop command and it's hard to model the
variables out if you're dealing with an
infrastructure tool like like Asia or
AWS they have published in documented
api's they spit out error messages that
that related to that that indicate the
relationship between multiple objects so
you can actually introspect that API and
knowing that in order to work with it
you know this sequence of Defense is
possible whereas puppet it's like harder
to introspect all of those different
tools and command line scripts and and
bits of configuration and make the same
determination so terraform tries to do
all of that for you hide the low need
that covers by doing that introspection
of the API and making that determination
however there are circumstances
particularly when you're dealing with
resources across example you might
human resources in Amazon Google cloud
and say a third-party DNS provider there
are some cases where terraform doesn't
know that there's a lot there should be
a relationship there which case you can
declare those dependencies you can
actually say do this thing before this
thing a really common example were using
the tariffs on royalties is um create
this new thing before you delete the old
thing so that's a common example like
your DNS entry it's like it's like no
make sure you you've um you've created
this new thing before you delete
developing because very clearly nothing
will break things or of course someone
unexpected behavior to happen Amazon
auto scaling group some another example
it's like make sure make sure you've got
a new version of this before you below
the old version allowing potentially to
stop the application James I can see if
I start out with a bunch of resources
and I have a bunch of facts like
resource a needs to come before B and B
needs to come before C and then
somewhere else I have X needs to come
before Y and Y needs to come before Z
and after we've created everything then
we're all done so I could turn that into
some kind of graph it seems like there
could be more than one possible graph
because not everything depends on
everything and so you could do things in
different ways is is there an algorithm
or are there known algorithms for graph
synthesis from these partial little
chunks of dependencies so this is where
mind all this starts to get a little bit
more theoretical there are definitely
ways of other public of achieving that
and but the interesting usually part for
me is that puppet and terraform both
have an actual way to visualize the
graph and this is something that I found
it's probably the easiest way to work
out what's going on is that you can
actually spit out a picture of of the
directed graph so you can actually say
if I make this change and make this
other change
write me a picture that shows all the
lines that joined together moment my
resources together it is certainly
possible less than less than puppet but
it certainly possible with their form to
use it like a library to include it in
something else and say make make reason
about the constructure underneath the
covers for me so for example I might
wonder why I might want to treat it as a
I might want to treat it as a way to
generate infrastructure for my platform
or my service underneath the covers like
I might want to create docker containers
or manage some sort of pool of resources
so there were definitely ways to
programmatically include Tara forms and
take and take advantage of its
capabilities there but as to the
specific algorithms I would I would have
to go and Google something for you it's
not an aerial I have an expertise okay I
have another graph related question I'm
building out a network we've talked a
lot about micro services which have
their own silo they have their own
storage say that I have my system it's
got five main subsystems and they're
somewhat independent of each other
there's no reason that I would need to
build them sequentially time to build
it's often minutes or if you add in
puppet runs can be tens of minutes for
infrastructure is terraform smart enough
to look at the graph and say this chunk
of the graph here chunk one chunk two
and chunk three they are all able to run
in parallel and they all need to be done
at some point before we can proceed and
say we're done but is it smart about
parallelism it is and so there's
obviously a couple of constraints like
for example it might be possible to
create those two resources in parallel
but the provider you use may not that
may not be capability it has so so the
we took the constraint in mind that
whatever infrastructure tool you're
using at the other end like Amazon or as
you may not allow you to paralyze those
operations
shimming that it does though for example
like you say i want to create a thousand
containments and it doesn't matter what
happening because I don't need them
until later when when they're used by
this load balancer so I'll create all of
those a paranoiac with a more simple
taneous Li rather than sequentially is
that the order is not important but I
won't create the load balancer until a
thousand containers are created before
that is something that I need to have in
sequence okay so we can save some time
and if somebody was trying to do this
with a script a ruby script instead of a
tool like terraform that adding in
parallelism and then synchronizing that
is a fairly complex type of programming
something they ask you about a lot in
programming job interviews because it's
easy to have subtle bugs yeah classic
old-school suits that means very
commonly good things parallel operations
by saying SSH into this a section secure
shell by creating a script than SSH to
like 30 machines simultaneously indeed
some action and then return the results
of that action and then you tracked
against this data somewhere so that was
a was a pretty common phenomena it was a
very fragile phenomena and one that you
know required a fair bit of hard coding
and sort of people lean to get right
I look at sort of massive parallel
operations like and sequencing
operations where you're trying to
maintain state or more importantly
passed the knowledge of one state to
another for example every one of those
thousand containers only drink I need to
return some information about the state
in order to populate the load balancer
for example IP address or its location
or path I possibly need to partner our
custom application figurations and
environment variables maybe some
authentication credentials and we need
to do that in such a way that I cannot
keep a running total of the number was
created the data associated with each
and then I need to make sure I step
through all of those and identify where
it hasn't worked and know that those are
those are reasonably complicated
dependency operations and honestly I I'm
glad that someone else has to work the
Cottam and except for me because
yes summer bugs definitely a problem but
even unstoppable often very hard to
diagnose in that epoch now that is a
great lead-in for another question I
want to ask you the how do you debug a
declarative program when you tell it
what you want
goes out and does all this stuff and
you're not getting the result that you
think you want what are some typical
debugging techniques
is there a debugger that's another
question is terraform have a debugger he
doesn't have a debugger in the classic
sort of programming language sense but
what what it does have is that well
first of all it's pretty good about and
thankfully most of these instructor
tools are pretty good about telling you
what went wrong so terraform will will
will try to do the best possible job you
can so in an imperative world like
usually if you get to the end of your
one of your steps fails probably the
whole program bombs out or worse the
program may continue and do something
unexpected because one of the steps
didn't work in the declarative world
like terraform generally speaking your
firewall off from the impact of that
because the resource that failed will
generally on the impact the resources
that are is connected to on the graph so
a good example of this is let's say I'm
creating that environment of my services
we're not all much services are
connected and let's say five out of six
of them six of them they're groups of
five or six resources that make up a
service and they're not interconnected
so if the sixth resource fails for some
reason let's say I ran out of capacity
on some like that and the sixth service
doesn't start terraform will happily
create the other five services and
report their success and next time I run
terraform it'll say oh no those are all
created I'll jump straight to the one
that needs help and I'll recreate that
or I'll create that so usually speaking
I'm only getting an error message
related to the thing that is broken I'm
getting out very clean in that all of
these other things got created with this
one thing didn't and all of the things
that I depended on that I know they're
not going to be I don't have to worry
about debugging them is there any god of
that to the farm bag resource if that
significantly shrinks the surface area
of my problem
and generally speaking I can now write
down to this final results didn't work
it didn't work cause it's about this
error fix that then everything that
always will be recreated or created and
all of my dependent resources will then
continue and any other errors over for
rather than imperative world where ten
things might have gone wrong and they
just have to sort of identify like how
finally to get in the script what
happened how do i interrogate that and
that's all recorded in careful to stay
file - so I can actually inspect the
state file and identify what you know it
didn't happen and for example I can do
things like because that state file is a
it's just a blob of objects I can do
things like I would like to edit that
state file to change something so that I
can actually work around the bug or I
think delete a whole resource so example
I'd like to for them to go back and
recreate this thing because I fixed the
problem I delete the resource I don't I
stay file I rerun terraform to reform
with Tara gates and safe answers only
that resource isn't there anymore
I should recreate that so it's very
powerful ways of sort of analyzing and
looking at that in a way you just can't
with an imperative heritage step by step
program in the example we've been
talking about where you have the five
micro services that can be created in
any order from what you're saying it
sounds like if it's smart about
parallelism it will get as much done as
it can in every independent branch you
don't have to decide I'm gonna create
these in order one two three four five
and Boop's
number one failed okay fix that now
number two failed you could find out a
lot of information about what went wrong
and proceeded on all the things that are
unblocked correct so you know often I
will identify something is going wrong
and why my terraform run i'll see an
error message on the screen it's not
like that but it was continued because
it has a little work to do I will jump
on to the console or jump on to the code
and I'll fix the problem careful and
finishes running and I just rerun it to
push the new change order or to make the
new change that I've identified live
okay now what language was terraform
implement
in its written go and do you know I'm
not sure if you were involved were you
involved in the product development at
any point I've been involved in as
having an opinion I would never not
claim to be you know what the primary
you probably move this behind it I will
say that I you know I had a fair bit to
say about public back in the day it was
one of people that worked on a lot of
that and I see a lot of that heritage in
terraform which pleases me what do you
think were lessons learned from puppet
that have made terraform what it is I
think probably the big one is is the
dependency the fancy model you know
being a long time puppet user on I'm
it's hard for me to sometimes be
empathetic towards people who are like
after you know I have to declare all the
dependencies because it's just instinct
to me I just know I talked it's like a
no you just talk about the you
need but definitely for people starting
with puppet like it was often very hard
to be like I ran my puppet run three
times and three different things
happened and you know I probably just
need to state what the dependencies are
and people like well that's silly why
doesn't it just no and I think that's
terrif one's been a big stumbling block
a lot of people adopting puppet that is
less so about terraform yeah and I think
that makes terraform quite attractive to
people because they don't have to worry
about the detail terraformable you know
99% of the time do the backbeat another
thing I've observed in puppet there's
something which sounds very similar in
spirit to me to provider where if puppet
doesn't know about a certain type of
thing like I was dealing with something
in Linux called a capability there
wasn't that wasn't known to puppet you
can write a custom piece of Ruby that
enables you to declaratively say
capability of this user to do some
operation on this process you can that's
moderate amount of work but there's this
Universal escape hatch where you can say
run this program is called exec
and it will escape from the declarative
world into the
parrot of world and just do this side
thing that who knows what it does what
side effects it has is there some kind
of an escape hatch out of the
declarative world in terraform sort of
less so than perhaps but to be really a
terraforming puppet very similar tools
but probably do subtly different
slightly different things terraform is
much more focused on infrastructure so
it's much more of a sort of you know
services databases message queues DNS
entries sort of mobile puppet is much my
name dead thickened individual
configuration items like for example
this this is the this is the IP address
of my MTV server this is the IP address
of the authentication server let's
populate that into my application
configuration so terraform as a concept
called provisioners and provisioners are
include very similar than what you
described and in fact it is even called
exec where allows you to run an
arbitrary command perform some action
you can also use things like exec to
connect to existing configuration
management tools so I can for example
create a bunch of servers with terraform
and then launch puppet on those servers
to do my more granular configuration and
that that allows me to sort of address
the things that you know I'm not sort of
available as resources I can mini fight
those terrible also has a concept of
very similar puppet of templating so I
can do things like create configuration
files configuration object as templates
and then I can pass it variables and be
careful and populate those templates so
example I might create a configuration
file that I would like to include on the
server inside terraform and use Tara
forms can play function to write that to
the server okay I wanted to finish up
with something that might be a bit
philosophical one of my other hosts on
the show point out to me that
declarative programming is becoming
increasingly popular the field of
programming itself is every year
becoming more specialized and has more
niches depending on where you worked and
what you worked on you know certain
languages so
systems and not other systems do you see
a point where there will be people whose
job is programmer and they don't need to
know an imperative language at all or to
use these tools do you really need to
understand what it's doing at the bottom
layer and it's saving you a lot of time
but you could do it yourself if you
needed to those people are already here
I've worked with a number of data people
for example who are amazing with SQL can
do incredible things with it I have no
idea how it outa base works they have no
idea about scaling the database or even
how its configured and they have no idea
what happens to you know under sort of
superficial level some of the very smart
do but a lot of them have no idea about
the detail underneath the surface but
they know how to turn a multi-line
hugely complex SQL query into a
consumable report so those people exist
here and now and I think there are in
our current world a number of engineers
for example who combine high-level
functions and libraries into into
components into other things and you
could argue anyone working in the Dom I
even work in the sort of the fermion
world where they're working their
browser Dom is in fact you know they
don't really you know it's a virtual
machine that displays content if you
like they don't know how the article I
asked most modern engineers there's a
fairly loose understanding of what's
happening underneath to do the junior
ones and the common question of what
happens when you talk on URL into the
browser and hit enter as a common
interview question I find that at a
certain level what I consider for the
backend or the infrastructure a lot of
fun engineers are fairly hazy about
what's happened but it's like the
gumline over very well having that you
feel like that and do that and they
don't need to live knows a low-level
detail because someone else takes care
of that I didn't necessarily see that as
a bad thing but I'm guessing is
something that that's likely to increase
you know we all know we all tend to be
reasonably the industry tends to is we
specialized things that's huge bodies of
knowledge I'm very skeptical that full
stack engineer term for example I think
there's a spectrum I'm definitely on the
infrastructure back in engineer side of
things
no one's gonna ever make me design
something or write JavaScript if they
can avoid it but I know lots of back-end
engineers who maybe aren't as
infrastructure centric isn't me but
notice some back-end stuff like lots of
Ruby on Rails develops knows the back
and stuff but a sufficiently skilled
that they can sort of reach up into the
JavaScript world and maybe the design
world a little bit but they definitely
couldn't debug a kernel problem so I
think that that that spectrum will
always exist and definitely people will
build abstraction layers that other
people will put together and that's a
natural evolution that's a great place
to stop James before we wrap up could
you tell us sinners where they can find
your books and where can they find you
on the web
sure I'm on twitter as kar ta are the
terraform walk is available at terraform
book.com it's also available on Amazon
Google and Luke look anyone still uses
look and I don't think so I don't decide
that's but I still gave it there I can't
be a minute in a blue moon and generally
speaking all of my sites and so forth
are linked from one of those always
happy give you from readers always happy
to hear from folks who have have
feedback about the books I've written or
ideas that would make them better what
my process is very collaborative where
possible and I'm always keen to
different folks who struggle through
something or didn't understand something
I very much time for that sort of brand
new beginner community all of my books
are particularly their terraform and
other books were generally aimed at or
are aimed at absolute beginners you've
why I don't expect you've ever seen
terraform before you start reading the
book so I'm always too keen to hear from
people when they have struggles and
challenges or things like it might
easier we are adopting terraform and my
current job I'm definitely in that
beginner category I've read the book and
I can attest it is definitely aimed at
somebody getting started and terraform
and will get you from the zero to the
one in that technology so really
encourage people to read that book is
anything else you'd like to say James
before we finish no thank you very much
again that's one of my favorite podcasts
are really Jarvan here thank you so much
for speaking to us at software
engineering radio for software joining
radio this has been Robert bloomin thank
you for listening
[Music]
help us make se radio even better by
completing our short listener survey at
WWE Triple E org slash se radio thanks
thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening